<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="article-commentary"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Immunother Cancer</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Immunother Cancer</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jitc</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jitc</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal for Immunotherapy of Cancer</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2051-1426</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name><publisher-loc>BMA House, Tavistock Square, London, WC1H 9JR</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">12458764</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jitc-2024-010530</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jitc-2024-010530</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Commentary</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>2520</subject><subject>1506</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Second signals for cancer immunotherapy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6857-5554</contrib-id><name><surname>Olejniczak</surname><given-names>Scott H.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3988-5419</contrib-id><name><surname>Lotze</surname><given-names>Michael T.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Skokos</surname><given-names>Dimitris</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="cor3" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Immunology</institution>, <institution>Roswell Park Comprehensive Cancer Center</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Buffalo</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">New York</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">Departments of Surgery, Immunology, and Bioengineering</institution>, <institution>University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Pittsburgh</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Pennsylvania</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Regeneron Pharmaceuticals Inc</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Tarrytown</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">New York</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Dr Michael T. Lotze; <email xlink:href="lotzemt@upmc.edu">lotzemt@upmc.edu</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2">Dr Scott H. Olejniczak; <email xlink:href="scott.olejniczak@roswellpark.org">scott.olejniczak@roswellpark.org</email></corresp><corresp id="cor3">Dimitris Skokos; <email xlink:href="dimitris.skokos@regeneron.com">dimitris.skokos@regeneron.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn3"><p>SHO has no competing interests. DS is a full-time employee of Regeneron, Inc. MTL is on the scientific advisory boards of AppelSauce, iRepertoire, BioCytics, KSQ, Zola Therapeutics, the Ludwig Institute, and ZaiLabs.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e010530</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2025. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="jitc-13-9.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Recent years have seen renewed appreciation of the critical role played by the prototypic T cell co-stimulatory receptor CD28 in cancer immunotherapy. Inhibition of co-stimulation by direct competition, as exemplified by cytotoxic T-lymphocyte associated protein 4 (CTLA-4) competition with CD28 for B7 ligands, or interference with intracellular signaling, such as that mediated by SHP2 phosphatase recruited to programmed cell death protein-1 (PD-1), provides tumors with a means to avoid elimination by cytotoxic T cells. Reversing this inhibition or providing co-stimulation by alternative means&#x02014;bispecific antibodies, chimeric antigen receptors, etc&#x02014;is the mechanistic basis behind the success of many modern cancer immunotherapies. As such, understanding the complexities of T cell co-stimulation and the various receptors driving it has taken on new importance. In this commentary, we highlight recent studies in this space and discuss their contributions to our understanding of T cell co-stimulatory receptors in cancer.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Immune Checkpoint Inhibitor</kwd><kwd>Immunotherapy</kwd><kwd>Major histocompatibility complex - MHC</kwd><kwd>T cell</kwd><kwd>co-stimulatory molecules</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100031022</institution-id><institution>Center for Cancer Research</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>The authors thank the careful review by their coll</award-id></award-group></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Second signals</title><p> The two-signal model of lymphocyte activation accounting for self-nonself discrimination, dating back to proposals by Bretscher and Cohn,<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> has borne the test of time. The notion then was that antigen was the requisite signal one and that a so-called &#x0201c;carrier effect&#x0201d; was necessary to overcome tolerance or cell death and initiate full activation. For T cells, we now understand that this &#x0201c;carrier effect&#x0201d; is primarily provided by antigen-presenting cells expressing coreceptor ligands. As we discuss here, how this two-signal system emerged evolutionarily and how various coreceptors functionally interact is still subject to extensive study, as the second signal provides a foundation for modern cancer immunotherapies.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref></p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Emergence of second signals in osteichthyes</title><p>When and how did co-stimulatory signaling elements emerge and what do they reveal about other co-stimulatory molecules, related and worthy of study? This has recently been considered by Flajnik, Boudinot, and colleagues.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> The evolution of vertebrates involved gene duplication events that diversified co-stimulatory molecules important for T-cell signaling. Clear evidence of CD28 can be found in Osteichthyes ranging from teleost fish (salmon, flounder, European sea bass, river pufferfish, Nile tilapia, rock bream, rainbow trout) to coelacanths to humans. In contrast, only CD28/cytotoxic T-lymphocyte-associated protein 4 (CTLA-4)-related sequences could be found in Chondrichthyes (jawless fish/lamprey). Teleost fish also possess a single B7 molecule interacting with CD28/CTLA-4. Summarizing a large amount of data, the extant and retained B7 family members in human include not only CD28 and CTLA-4 but also inducible T cell costimulator (ICOS), CD28H, and more distantly, programmed cell death protein-1 (PD-1). CD28H is widely expressed on natural killer (NK) and T cells with the primary activating ligand being HHLA2, widely expressed on normal epithelia and variably lost on tumor cells. KIR3DL3 serves as an inhibitory ligand for CD28H. Such less well-studied B7 family molecules have potential as novel co-stimulatory domains in chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) constructs and/or as targets of agonistic antibodies, promoting their role in immuno-oncology.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Second signal delivery within the tumor</title><p>A lingering question in cancer immunology is how cytotoxic CD8 T cells (CTL) are activated in tumors that are generally lacking in expression of ligands for CD28.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> The notion that CTL arise in tumor-draining lymph nodes (TDLN) and subsequently traffic to tumors where they do not require additional co-stimulation has been challenged by studies demonstrating that CD8 T cells activated in TDLN remain in a stem-like state and require further T-cell receptor (TCR) and co-stimulation in the tumor microenvironment (TME) to differentiate into functional CTLs.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> The source of co-stimulation in the TME is thought to be CD28, but conclusive evidence of this is lacking. Dong <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> have recently reported that the NK receptors (NKR) CD226 (DNAM1) and to a lesser extent CD314 (NKG2D) provide co-stimulatory signals to human CTLs on encountering cancer cells that express NKR ligands and &#x0201c;weak&#x0201d; tumor-associated antigens displayed on major histocompatibility complex I. Interestingly, NKR ligands are upregulated on tumor cells in response to chemotherapy and their ligation with NKRs on CTLs lowers TCR functional avidity. The resulting induction of effector genes and polyfunctional effector cytokine production in CD226, and to a lesser extent CD314 co-stimulated CTLs suggests that NKR may have the potential to stimulate CTL differentiation in the TME. These results are in line with earlier work showing that CD226 on CTLs stimulated response to &#x003b1;PD-1 (or &#x003b1;T cell immunoglobulin and ITIM domain [TIGIT]) immune checkpoint blockade (ICB) therapy.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref></p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Convergence of effective immunotherapies on the CD28 response</title><p>CD28 (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>) underlies response to &#x003b1;PD-1 (or &#x003b1;CTLA-4) ICB therapy<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> and both CD28 and CD226 are targets of dephosphorylation by PD-1 associated SHP2 phosphatase. Interestingly, the expression pattern of CD28 and CD226 on tumor-infiltrating CD8 T cells from patients with lung cancer (both found in KLRB1-expressing T cells with stem-like properties)<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> indicates that the differential ability of T-cell subsets to respond to ICB therapy may be dictated by available co-stimulatory receptors and the downstream pathways they activate. An important caveat of this and similar studies is that they do not differentiate between tumor-reactive and bystander T cells in the TME, limiting their ability to link co-stimulatory receptor expression and response to ICB therapy. Dong <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> show that na&#x000ef;ve CD8 T cells respond most strongly to TCR+CD28 co-stimulation, while previously activated CTLs respond most strongly to TCR+CD226 co-stimulation, supporting the notion that T-cell subsets respond to co-stimulatory signals differently. This is reminiscent of the relationship between CD28 and ICOS signaling in T follicular helper cells (Tfh), with CD28 driving Tfh differentiation from na&#x000ef;ve and ICOS maintaining the function of mature Tfh cells.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Further study of differential and additive or converging effects of co-stimulatory molecules, including those discussed above along with other B7 (CD28H, etc), TNFR (4-1BB/CD137, CD27, etc), and immunoglobulin family (CD2, etc) proteins, on T-cell subsets and their interactions with checkpoint receptors is needed if we hope to optimize immunotherapeutic targeting of cancer through combination strategies aimed at maximally activating antitumor CTLs.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>CD28 activation is central to modern immunotherapy. The &#x0201c;second signal&#x0201d;, CD28 appears to be critical not only for mediating the response to immune checkpoint blockade (ICB) therapy and co-stimulating adoptively transferred tumor-infiltrating lymphocyte (TIL) and chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T-cell therapies, but also acts as a target for immune modulating small molecule inhibitors and therapeutic bispecific and trispecific antibodies being tested in the clinic.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Increased understanding of CD28 and other co-stimulatory molecules capable of delivering a &#x0201c;second signals&#x0201d; to T cells has the potential to further advance the field of immuno-oncology. CTLA-4, cytotoxic T-lymphocyte associated protein 4; PD-1, programmed cell death protein-1; PD-L1, programmed death-ligand 1.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="jitc-13-9-g001" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="s5"><title>CD28 co-stimulation in non-canonical cell types</title><p>An unappreciated and understudied aspect of co-stimulatory receptors is their expression and function on non-canonical cell types. As discussed above, receptors normally associated with NK cells when expressed on CD8 T cells may be important regulators of antitumor immunity.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4 5</sup></xref> Surprisingly, recent work demonstrates that CD28 is expressed as an intracellular protein in breast cancer cells where it promotes programmed death-ligand 1 expression and immune escape.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> This suggests a potential moonlighting cytosolic function of CD28 (and potentially other evolutionarily related family members). Additionally, it has long been appreciated that CD28 is expressed and functions as a survival signal on long-lived plasma cells in the bone marrow and on their malignant counterparts, multiple myeloma (MM) cells. A recent study by Peng <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> provides important mechanistic insight into how CD28 promotes MM cell survival under stress conditions, such as those encountered in the myeloma bone marrow microenvironment. This study finds that when available extracellular long-chain fatty acids (LCFA)&#x02014;a key fuel source for MM cells&#x02014;are limited, CD28 activation of a Ca<sup>2+</sup> &#x02192; AMPK &#x02192; ULK1 axis promotes lipophagy via induction of ATG5 translation and thereby provides MM cells a source of LCFA to maintain mitochondrial metabolism. Likewise, CD28 expression on T cells promoting TCR-stimulated Ca<sup>2+</sup> signaling<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> and AMPK has been implicated in T-cell mitochondrial metabolic adaptation and messenger RNA translation.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> Additional similarities between CD28 signaling in T cells and normal or malignant plasma cells have been observed, yet under physiological conditions CD28 acts as a co-receptor on T cells, cooperating with TCR engagement. Plasma/MM cells use CD28 as a stand-alone receptor. Further exploration of similarities and differences between CD28 signaling in T cells and plasma/MM cells has the potential to uncover fundamental aspects of co-stimulation that are difficult to separate from TCR effects in T cells.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Reemergence of CD28 targeted therapeutics</title><p>A promising recent emergence in immuno-oncology has been the finding that the life-threatening cytokine release syndrome induced by CD28 superagonists can be obviated using tumor-targeted CD28 bispecific and trispecific antibodies.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Such antibodies are being earnestly developed by several pharmaceutical firms and biotechnology companies. The findings of Peng and colleagues<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> should be taken into consideration when considering the best use of the various CD28 bispecific combination treatments in diseases such as MM. Furthermore, whether the findings of Dong and colleagues<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> should now be extended to consider CD226 and/or CD314<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> bispecific antibodies, particularly in the setting of progressive loss of CD28 expression on CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells with age, is an interesting supposition.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s7"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The success of modern cancer immunotherapy relies heavily on T-cell co-stimulation, with checkpoint inhibitors releasing the breaks on CD28 and potentially other second signals, integration of second signals in the cytosolic domains of CAR constructs, and bispecifics comprised of agonistic antibodies to CD28 coupled to tumor antigen specific antibodies recently entering the clinic. Continued basic and translational research aimed at finding means, such as application of Casitas B-lineage lymphoma proto-oncogene B (CBL-B) inhibitors to serve as faux second signals for modern tumor-infiltrating lymphocyte therapy<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> or the development of novel second signal agonists, has the potential to expand the immunotherapeutic arsenal for patients with cancer.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This work was supported, in part, by grants from NIAID (R01 AI155499 to SHO) and by the NCI Roswell Park Cancer Center Support Grant (P30 CA016056), as well as that to the University of Pittsburgh Hillman Cancer Center (P30 CA047904-35).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient consent for publication:</bold> Not applicable.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethics approval:</bold> Not applicable.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; internally peer reviewed.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bretscher</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A theory of self-nonself discrimination</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1970</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>1042</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.169.3950.1042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4194660</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lotze</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olejniczak</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Skokos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>CD28 co-stimulation: novel insights and applications in cancer immunotherapy</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><year>2024</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>878</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41577-024-01061-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39054343</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Quiniou</surname><given-names>SMA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bengt&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Extraordinary diversity of the CD28/CTLA4 family across jawed vertebrates</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>1501934</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2024.1501934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39606244</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Obermajer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>NK Receptor Signaling Lowers TCR Activation Threshold, Enhancing Selective Recognition of Cancer Cells by TAA-Specific CTLs</article-title><source>Cancer Immunol Res</source><year>2024</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1421</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/2326-6066.CIR-24-0061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38949179</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Banta</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chitre</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Mechanistic convergence of the TIGIT and PD-1 inhibitory pathways necessitates co-blockade to optimize anti-tumor CD8<sup>+</sup> T cell responses</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2022</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>512</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2022.02.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35263569</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fuhrmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feist</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>ICOS maintains the T follicular helper cell phenotype by down-regulating Kr&#x000fc;ppel-like factor 2</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>212</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20141432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25646266</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Inhibiting intracellular CD28 in cancer cells enhances antitumor immunity and overcomes anti-PD-1 resistance via targeting PD-L1</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2025</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccell.2024.11.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39672166</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chavel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Pro-survival signaling regulates lipophagy essential for multiple myeloma resistance to stress-induced death</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2024</year><volume>43</volume><elocation-id>114445</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2024.114445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38968073</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blagih</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coulombe</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The energy sensor AMPK regulates T cell metabolic adaptation and effector responses in vivo</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2015</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2014.12.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25607458</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Waite</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Tumor-targeted CD28 bispecific antibodies enhance the antitumor efficacy of PD-1 immunotherapy</article-title><source>Sci Transl Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>eaba2325</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.aba2325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32581132</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Herault</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de la Cruz-Chuh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>NKG2D-bispecific enhances NK and CD8+ T cell antitumor immunity</article-title><source>Cancer Immunol Immunother</source><year>2024</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>209</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00262-024-03795-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39112670</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coukos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><comment>n.d.</comment><article-title>The Science of Tumor Infiltrating Lymphocytes (TIL): Perspectives from the SITC Surgery Committee</article-title><source>J Immunother Cancer</source></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
