<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nlm2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Immunol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Immunology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-3224</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">12535959</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2025.1706172</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: Monitoring the immune/tumor microenvironment to improve cancer immunotherapy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Jinhwan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2598379/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kubelick</surname><given-names>Kelsey P.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2725842/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
<institution>Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of California, Davis</institution>, <addr-line>Davis, CA</addr-line>,&#x000a0;<country>United States</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
<institution>Department of Surgery, School of Medicine, University of California, Davis</institution>, <addr-line>Sacramento, CA</addr-line>,&#x000a0;<country>United States</country>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
<institution>Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of Virginia</institution>, <addr-line>Charlottesville, VA</addr-line>,&#x000a0;<country>United States</country>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited and reviewed by: <ext-link xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/302868/overview" ext-link-type="uri">Peter Brossart</ext-link>, University of Bonn, Germany</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Jinhwan Kim, <email xlink:href="mailto:jjnkim@ucdavis.edu">jjnkim@ucdavis.edu</email>; Kelsey P. Kubelick, <email xlink:href="mailto:kpkubelick@virginia.edu">kpkubelick@virginia.edu</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>1706172</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 Kim and Kubelick.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kim and Kubelick</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article related-article-type="commentary-article" id="RA1" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/64297" ext-link-type="uri" journal-id="Front Immunol" journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Editorial on the Research Topic <article-title>Monitoring the immune/tumor microenvironment to improve cancer immunotherapy</article-title>
</related-article><kwd-group><kwd>cancer immunotherapy</kwd><kwd>tumor microenvironment</kwd><kwd>biosensor</kwd><kwd>monitoring tumor</kwd><kwd>immune cell tracking</kwd><kwd>monitoring immune responses</kwd><kwd>theranostics</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001"><institution-wrap><institution>National Cancer Institute
</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000054</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id award-type="contract" rid="cn001">R00CA263016</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002"><institution-wrap><institution>UVA Cancer Center
</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100017397</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn003"><institution-wrap><institution>Brain Institute, University of Virginia
</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100017460</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="6"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="938"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>section-in-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Cancer Immunity and Immunotherapy</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Although cancer immunotherapies have demonstrated remarkable clinical success across various cancer types, their potential is constrained by heterogeneous patient responses and immune-related toxicities (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). An effective immune response against cancer necessitates the coordinated activity of multiple cellular and molecular mediators within the cancer-immunity cycle, which encompasses antigen release and presentation, immune cell priming, their trafficking and infiltration, and ultimately tumor cell killing (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Unfortunately, each step can be impacted by the immunosuppressive tumor microenvironment (TME), and failure at any single step can lead to resistance or relapse.</p><p>It is important to recognize that the TME is not a static compartment but a dynamic ecosystem where malignant cells, immune effectors, vasculature, and soluble mediators interact in both synergistic and antagonistic ways (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Traditional methods of studying the immune response within the TME, such as invasive biopsy-based histological analyses or snapshot-like endpoint assays, fail to capture the spatiotemporal dynamics and heterogeneity that shape clinical outcomes (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Recent advancements in bioimaging, biosensing, and computational modeling now enable us to observe the immune response in real-time, non-invasively, and longitudinally (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). This allows us to map cell-cell interactions <italic>in situ</italic>, monitor therapeutic interventions based on the imaging feedback, and link these observations to patient outcomes. This Research Topic includes 12 contributions (6 original research articles, 3 reviews, 2 mini-reviews, and 1 opinion piece) that collectively illustrate the cutting-edge technologies for visualizing and quantifying the complex spatiotemporal dynamics of the immune-tumor microenvironment. These advanced imaging and diagnostic strategies offer profound insights into mechanisms of resistance, guide the optimization of current cancer immunotherapies, and inspire novel treatment strategies.</p><p>A comprehensive review article by <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2025.1621812" ext-link-type="uri">Racacho et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> framed the tumor/immune microenvironment (TIME) as a central determinant of cancer progression and therapeutic response, describing how cellular and molecular interactions drive immune activation or suppression and how modern immunotherapies aim to reprogram these processes. Moreover, their study highlighted emerging trends in imaging and artificial intelligence (AI) that enable precise visualization of immune dynamics, setting the stage for research advances in this field. A complementary mini-review article by <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2025.1611861" ext-link-type="uri">Purl et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> focused on adoptive cellular therapies for liver metastases, emphasizing how the hepatic niche restricts immune cell trafficking and persistence and how advanced imaging platforms, including PET and MRI, can be leveraged to track and optimize therapeutic cell delivery.</p><p>Articles in this Research Topic also emphasized the significance of direct visualization of immune responses. Opinion, review, and research articles by <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2025.1609606" ext-link-type="uri">Zhang et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link>, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2024.1428541" ext-link-type="uri">Zhang et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link>, and <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2024.1480091" ext-link-type="uri">Frecot et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> underscored the need to move beyond static endpoints and adopt spatiotemporal imaging techniques. These techniques, including multiplex tissue imaging, intravital microscopy, and PET tracers targeting CD8 or OX40 to image T cell status, enabled longitudinal and functional monitoring for the identification of earlier and more accurate indicators of therapeutic response.</p><p>Advanced imaging strategies have led to the identification of new structural features within the immune-tumor microenvironment. For example, tertiary lymphoid structures (TLS) can serve as organizational centers that underpin therapeutic responses, highlighting their potential role as predictive biomarkers of cancer immunotherapy. In the context of ovarian cancer, a review article by <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2025.1473969" ext-link-type="uri">Varghese et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> presented evidence linking TLS, improved survival, and responsiveness to checkpoint blockade therapies. In contrast, a research article by <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2025.1500792" ext-link-type="uri">Munoz-Erazo et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> demonstrated how digital pathology methods can be utilized in colorectal cancer to standardize TLS analysis and correlate with clinical outcomes.</p><p>Advancements in computational modeling and molecular profiling have further expanded monitoring capabilities. A research article by <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2025.1540013" ext-link-type="uri">Liu et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> showcased how a multimodal deep learning framework that integrates pathology, radiology, and clinical data enhanced the prediction of PD-L1 status, immunotherapy response, and survival in esophageal cancer, demonstrating the power of AI-driven data fusion. Complementary bioinformatics and single-cell studies revealed microenvironment-linked biomarkers across tumor types. For instance, research articles by <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2025.1578243" ext-link-type="uri">Zheng et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> found RFC4 overexpression in lung adenocarcinoma, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2025.1492541" ext-link-type="uri">Huang et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> identified disulfidptosis/ferroptosis-related gene signatures in endometrial carcinoma, and <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2024.1513076" ext-link-type="uri">Miao et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> identified high FGF12 expression in stromal sarcoma. These findings emphasize the importance of interpreting tumor-intrinsic biology through the lens of the immune context. The microenvironment ultimately determines whether molecular changes translate into therapeutic vulnerability.</p><p>Finally, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2024.1431495" ext-link-type="uri">Wang et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> provided a mini-review that exemplifies the context-specific nature of immune regulation. Their review focused on IL-37 in gastrointestinal disease, highlighting how this cytokine&#x02019;s effects vary depending on the tissue and disease stage. This complexity underscores the importance of tailoring immunotherapy strategies to the unique characteristics of local immune environments.</p><p>Together, the contributions in this Research Topic highlight how the field of cancer immunotherapy monitoring is evolving through a deeper understanding and real-time assessment of the tumor/immune microenvironment. Articles in this Research Topic demonstrate how non-invasive imaging can capture the dynamics of immune engagement, how to standardize and utilize TLS as actionable biomarkers, how to integrate multimodal approaches and leverage AI to enhance predictive power, how bioinformatics and single-cell approaches can reveal novel immune-linked targets, and how context-specific regulation continues to complicate and enrich our understanding of the tumor/immune microenvironment. Effective cancer immunotherapy demands a united effort to design potent interventions along with tools to monitor, visualize, and guide immune responses as they unfold within the tumor microenvironment.</p><p>Finally, we would like to express our gratitude to all of the authors and reviewers for their invaluable contributions to this Research Topic. Their work exemplifies the growing power of interdisciplinary collaboration that integrates immunology, oncology, radiology, engineering, and data science to advance cancer immunotherapy through real-time monitoring of the tumor/immune microenvironment.</p></body><back><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>JK: Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. KK: Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s2"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ai-statement" id="s3"><title>Generative AI statement</title><p>The author(s) declare that no Generative AI was used in the creation of this manuscript.</p><p>Any alternative text (alt text) provided alongside figures in this article has been generated by Frontiers with the support of artificial intelligence and reasonable efforts have been made to ensure accuracy, including review by the authors wherever possible. If you identify any issues, please contact us.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s4"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sambi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagheri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Szewczuk</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Current challenges in cancer immunotherapy: multimodal approaches to improve efficacy and patient response rates</article-title>. <source>J Oncol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>2019</volume>:<elocation-id>4508794</elocation-id>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2019/4508794</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 30941175?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30941175</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The history and advances in cancer immunotherapy: understanding the characteristics of tumor-infiltrating immune cells and their therapeutic implications</article-title>. <source>Cell Mol Immunol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<page-range>807&#x02013;21</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41423-020-0488-6</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 32612154?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32612154</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murciano-Goroff</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name><name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolchok</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The future of cancer immunotherapy: microenvironment-targeting combinations</article-title>. <source>Cell Res</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<page-range>507&#x02013;19</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41422-020-0337-2</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 32467593?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32467593</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukarrama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Recent advances in non-invasive <italic>in vivo</italic> tracking of cell-based cancer immunotherapies</article-title>. <source>Biomater Sci</source>. (<year>2025</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<page-range>1939&#x02013;59</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/d4bm01677g</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 40099377?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40099377</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kubelick</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>
<italic>In vivo</italic> ultrasound and photoacoustic imaging of nanoparticle-engineered T cells and post-treatment assessment to guide adoptive cell immunotherapy</article-title>. <source>ACS Nano</source>. (<year>2025</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<page-range>6079&#x02013;94</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsnano.4c12929</pub-id>, PMID: <?supplied-pmid 39908484?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39908484</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Castellanos</surname><given-names>AMS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jhunjhunwala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nanoengineered cytotoxic T cells for photoacoustic image-guided combinatorial cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>BioMed Eng Lett</source>. (<year>2025</year>). doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13534-025-00499-z</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
